Leah: So maybe you have always
had an interest in computers
and dabbled in coding.
Let's have a look at how you could
take this interest forward and develop
a career in coding and programming.
There are plenty of different
jobs out there for programmers
in the world of technology.
Remember all those computer
games and apps you like playing,
software developers created them.
Think of all the industries
that use different software
and it all must be programmed.
So, let's have a look at some of
those jobs and career paths that
you could follow and what they
involve and what qualifications
you need to apply for a role.
Jack: Software application developers are
responsible for creating and enhancing
applications for mobile devices and the
most common programming languages for this
role are Java, Java script and Python.
Leah: Web developers work on the
look and function of websites.
They listen to the client’s needs and
problem solve to give them the best
website for their business needs, they
will work with a range of other creatives
to optimise the best fit for a client.
Most common languages used for creating
website are Java, Java Script, and HTML.
Jack: Computer systems engineers are
responsible for taking complex application
problems, system administration
issues or network concerns and
identifying and creating solutions.
They work closely with the client
and collaborate with developers.
Most common languages
are Python, Java, and C++
Leah: Database administrators are
responsible for securing, organising,
and troubleshooting large amounts of data
storage for companies or organisations.
This is a great role for those who
like to analyse, and problem solve.
Most common languages are
Python, Java, and SQL.
Jack: Computer systems analysts
are strategists who are
responsible for merging a company's
business and IT initiatives.
The evaluate and propose upgrades
to meet the growing business needs.
As well as coding, a good
knowledge of business is useful.
Most common languages are
Python, Java, and JavaScript
Leah: Software quality assurance engineers
are involved at the creation of software,
documenting defects and designing tests
and scenarios and creating manuals.
They review functionality
and potential problems.
Most common languages are
Python, Java and JavaScript.
Jack: For a Business Intelligence analyst,
programming is a bonus but not always
necessary, as they determine trends and
gather facts about software products.
This is an ideal career for those
who don't always want to code.
Most common languages are Python and Java.
Leah: Computer Programmers
write and rewrite programmes
until they are free of errors.
They use workflow charts and
coding formulas and show a good
attention to detail and patience.
Most common languages are
Java and JavaScript and C#
Jack: Network system administrators
maintain computing environments
in their networks and prevent
disasters by backing up data.
They also provide network security and
make sure that codes are free of errors.
Most common languages are Python and Java.
Leah: Most people go into this career
path after graduating after doing a degree
in IT, Computing or other STEM subjects.
There are also courses available in coding
and specialist events and bootcamps.
Some organisations also offer
apprenticeship routes into a coding
career with on-the-job experience.
Once a programmer has their foot on
the ladder then the opportunities for
progression are there, depending on their
abilities to expand their knowledge base
and experience and those with advanced
skills are likely to be in great demand.